A Finding Aid to the Bessie S. Callender Papers, circa 1880s-1955, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Bessie S. Callender papers
circa 1880s-1955
Archives of American Art
Callender, Bessie Stough, 1889-1951
AAA.callbess
Archival Resource Key
0.8 Linear feet
The papers of sculptor Bessie S. Callender measure 0.8 linear feet and date from circa 1880s-1955. The papers focus on Callender's personal life and travel and include biographical materials, two books, correspondence, and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
Bessie S. Callender (1889-1951) was a sculptor known for her direct carving of animals. Born in Kansas, Callender studied in New York City and married reporter Harold Callender. The Callenders travelled abroad and lived in London.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Scope and Contents
The papers of sculptor Bessie S. Callender measure 0.8 linear feet and date from circa 1880s-1955. The papers focus on Callender's personal life and travel and include biographical materials, two books, correspondence, and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was transferred to the Archives of American Art from the National Collection of Fine Arts on June 6, 1979.
Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; Animal sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; Women artists; Women sculptors; Callender, Harold, 1892-1959
- Bessie S. Callender Papers, circa 1880s-1955; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical materials include a passport, a diary from 1946, a receipt, and writings on Callender compiled by her husband, Harold Callender. A book entitled Fun Tomorrow: The Story of an Artist and of a Way of Life, is by Harold Callender concerning his wife and her career. Also found is a book of poetry owned by Bessie Callender. Correspondence is from friends and family and largely dates from 1950 to 1951. Letters discuss travel, family news and updates, and get well wishes to Callender. The bulk of the collection consists of photographs including: portraits of Bessie Callender, Harold Callender as an infant, and other members of the Callender family; snapshots of travel in England, France, Switzerland, and throughout the United States, particularly within National Parks; photos of works of art; and photos of other family, friends, dogs, castles, gardens, and homes. Also found are empty negative envelopes, some of which note locations.
  - Biographical Material, 1913-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Books, 1937-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, Portraits of Bessie Callender, circa 1930s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, Portraits of Callender Family, circa 1880-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, Snapshots, circa 1930-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Photographs, Snapshots, circa 1930-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, Snapshots, Dogs, circa 1930-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - Photographs, Negative Envelopes, 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4-5)